How can you even survive on 170
Как вы вообще на 170
dollars? Well, we still have benefits, I
долларов выживает Ну мы ещё посо я
still have benefits, well, there are
пособи по пособие же ещё есть просто ну
also a bit of benefits there. Well, 14,000 for
пос там же тоже немного Ну 14.000 на
each child.
каждого ребёнка
Wow, I don’t know. Shikova, it’s possible if
Ого это можно не знаю шикова можно если
it’s not like our children’s parents.
если это не как детские наши родители Да
Yes, yes, well, look  this is if you make 100 children,
получали да Ну смотри это если 100 детей
yes, then you can have a month
сделать да то можно в месяц иметь
Hello Hello I am originally from
здравствуйте Здравствуйте Я сам родом из
Rostov But I have been living for 18 years in California
Ростова Но живу 18 лет в Калифорнии
in 2 years it will be where you are
через 2 года будет дто Вы
from We are not far from Rostov from where in
откуда Мы недалеко от Ростова откуда
short Circassia I know I know damn it my
короче Черкесия знаю знаю блин у меня
father served in Kabardino Balkaria in
отец служил в Кабардино Балкарии в
Karachaevo  Circassia is just
Карачаево Черкесии как раз
in time for you
при выды
[music]
[музыка]
Well, are you Circassian, yes or no? And tea, yes, I
Ну черкески вы да или нет А чаев да
understand,
понял
just a second,
секундочку
come in and sit now, let’s go home too
заходи посиди сейчас тоже домой пойдём
How are you doing? How are you living
Как у вас дела Как как как живётся
normally in America? You’re 18 years old.
нормально в Америке жи вам 18 лет есть
So let me clarify at 23 super cheat you can
Так уточню на 23 супер чит можно
talk, yes  it turns out that you are
разговаривать да вы получается вы
Karachais - a Turkic people or
карачаевцы - это тюркский народ или
what kind of Turkic Dagu it just
какой да да тюркский дагу просто
turns out that they are Circassians, they are Adygs like A
получается черкесы они Адыги типа А
in short, yes, it’s the same as Kabardian
короче да это также как кабардина
Balkaria Yes Kabarda are Circassians and Balkars are
Балкарии Да Кабарда черкесы а балкарцы
Turks Yes, that’s right Your names are Jurassic
тюрки Да всё верно У вас имена Юрские
or Russian, well I have a Russian name
или русские хорошо у меня русское имя А
Why  I
почему
don’t know. My parents called it
так не знаю Родители так назвали
Sofia Sofia or Sofia Sofia Sofia, yes. Well,
София София или София София София да Ну
it’s a Greek name in general, and I understand Greek and
это греческое имя вообще да греческое и
Russian. Close the door,
русское понял Закрой дверь
please, and you speak Russian well.
пожалуйста а вы прямо по-русски хорошо
I’m from Rostov. I’m from Rostov. I’ve
разговариваете Я из Ростова родом Я
just been living in America for 18 years in
просто 18 лет живу в Америке в
California for 18 years. 18  years, if I
Калифорнии 18 лет 18 лет если бы я в
lived in America for 18 years, it doesn’t seem to
Америке жила 18 лет Мне кажется всё
matter to me. Well, I’m 43. Look, I lived in Russia for 25 years,
равно Ну мне 43 Смотри я 25 лет жил в
and for 18 years in America. Of course, I
России да и 18 лет в Америке Конечно я я
watch Russian news anyway.
новости смотрю российские всё равно
I communicate here in America with the Russian community;
Общаюсь тут в Америке с русской общиной
we call each other; how are you doing?  life in
созваниваемся да как у вас там жизнь в
Karachaevo Circassian Yes, everything is fine
Карачаево черкес Да всё хорошо
little by little how much
потихонечку сколько
salary is not enough don’t put pressure on the patient Well,
зарплаты мало не давите на больное Ну
why are
зачем тут просто
you just a living wage of a penny
вы прожиточный минимум копейки
17800 no well yes well I just saw that the
17800 не ну да ну а я просто видел что
minimum wage is something like 19000 yes And
минимальная зарплата чтото 19000 да А
how much salary do you really
сколько реально у вас
get Jean I yes Well
зарплата вот получаешь Жан я да Ну
In general, the cost of living, it
вообще прожиточный минимум он
goes no, the cost of living now is 19-
идёт нет прожиточный минимум сейчас э 19
something Well, there’s also a tax of 13%, and
с чем-то Ну там же ещё налог 13% да и у
I have like two children, I’m generally 17,200
меня как двое детей я вообще 17200
somewhere, and she’s a teacher of
где-то а она преподаватель
men’s eyes popping out of her head,
по мужчины глаза на лоб вылезли
and she’s a teacher of labor in  school,
а она преподаватель по трудам в школе
that is, a teacher at school receives a salary of 170
то есть на учитель в школе получает 170
dollars, it
долларов
turns out that in general, in our
зарплаты получается так да у нас вообще
Republic, in general, in terms of
в Республике вообще вот по
regions,
субъектам м самые низкие
salaries are the lowest. And this may be your
зарплаты просто А это может это у вас
rate is lower, or this is
меньше ставки или это
the rate, this is the rate, my rate And this is
ставка это ставка у меня ставка А это
17,000 in your hands  in mind Yes yes yes And
17000 на руки имеете в виду Да да да А
well, I understand, that is, it turns out that they actually
ну понял то есть получается реально там
charge you somewhere around 1920 And in your hands it
где-то 1920 вам начисляют А на руки
turns out 17 Well, yes That’s where the tax goes.
получается 17 Ну да Там же налог уходит
survives
а как вы вообще на 170 долларов выживает
Well, we still have for me for sobi for sozhe still
Ну мы ещё по я по соби по по соже ещ
have just a little for each child Well, 14,000 for
есть просто по тоже немного Ну 14.000 на
each child
каждого ребёнка
Wow, this is possible, I don’t know Shikova, it’s possible if
Ого это можно не знаю шикова можно если
it’s not like a child’s, our parents Yes, they
это не как детский наши родители Да
received it, yes Well, look at this, if you
получали де да Ну смотри это если 100
do 100 children, yes, then you can
детей сделать да то можно в месяц
to have a month Well, there are a lot of them, and there are three of them each Well,
иметь Ну таких много вон и по трое по Ну
there are three of us Well, it’s clear that no one is paying me for
вот нас мне трое Ну понятно там на на
a long time No one has been getting anything for me, but it’s
меня никто Давно ничего не получает но
small Yes, it works out for small ones,
мелкие Да на мелких получается да
look, it’s just that I work in
смотрите вот просто я работаю в
California I’m a university teacher
Калифорнии Я преподаватель университета
teaching anthropology I have a small
антропологию преподаю У меня небольшая
salary  per month 99,000 dollars is
зарплата в месяц 99.000 долларов это
in Russian 900,000 rubles per month and I
по-российски 900.000 руб в месяц и Я
when I hear and I think it’s small We
когда слышу и я считаю маленькой У нас
have at our university we have more,
есть у нас в университете есть больше
it’s just that I have a short experience Yes, I’ve
это просто у меня небольшой стаж Да я
recently been working in America, yes,
недавно как бы работаю в Америке да э
there are, and there are even more lawyers  they also get it
есть а юристы ещё больше получают ещё и
when I hear Yes, 170 dollars is the salary of a
когда я слышу Да 170 долларов зарплата
teacher in Russia, my eyes
учителя в России у меня глаза на лоб
really pop out of my head, how can this be? Well, I
лезут реально как такое может быть Ну я
work in a restaurant. I have 7 names of
вот работаю в ресторане У меня 7 наме
medicine. For example, we have free
медицина У нас например бесплатная
medicine. And there are many such factors
медицина А много же таких факторов то
that we don’t pay  and our tax is still
что мы не платим и налог у нас всё равно
less than in Ari with Kak Kak Do you
меньше чем в Ари с Как Как Как вам
think you would like to receive 900,000
кажется вы бы хотели получать 900.000
rubles and have paid medicine or
руб и иметь платную медицину или
receive 17,000 rubles and
получать 17.000 руб и вот эту бесплатную
I have this free medicine, that’s how many bloggers I
медицина у меня вот сколько блогеров я
see, some go to America on purpose,
смотрю некоторые специально едут в
people get it on purpose
Америку люди специально получают
citizenship so that someone there something
гражданство чтобы кто-то там что-то
someone
кого-то
medicine BC anyway they are far away ours are
медицина ВС равно у них далеко наша
far away BC anyway to their medicine here is a
далеко ВС равно до их медицины вот
girl I have a blogger I see she went
девушка у меня блогер я смотрю поехала
yes There they did something there they
да Там они там что-то сделали жить
started living there then they planned a child they
начали там потом запланировали ребёнка
planned for her  gave birth in
планировали чтобы она родила именно в
America, not in general, giving birth in Miami, they are the
Америке не вообще роды в Майами они же
most
самые
popular, so it turns out that for me,
популярные так получается у меня вот
too, my father receives a pension,
тоже у меня вот отец он пенсию получает
he receives
он получает
a nsi. And even then, well, damn, how I worked in Rostov.
нси Да и то это ну в Ростове блин как
I’m just here. Working in
проработал Я тут просто Работая в
America, I get 900,000 rubles for ours
Америке получаю 900.000 руб на наши
Russian money Yes, and he gets one who
русские деньги Да а он получает который
worked all his life at a factory Yes, a 20,000
проработал всю жизнь на заводе Да 20.000
ruble pension, what can he do here in
руб пенсию что он может сделать у нас в
America? Retired people can
Америке люди на пенсии могут себе
go on a cruise ship,
поездить на лайнере круизном
travel around the world, yes. But in Russia, they have
кругосветное путешествие да А в России
n’t lived and don’t live, and
что не жили и не живут да комуналку
pay for utilities, so  something to eat Well, well,
оплати так что-нибудь поесть Ну хорошо а
here’s how it turns out that we have Russia, the
вот как так получается у нас же Россия
richest country, oil gold gas
богатейшая страна нефть золото газ
diamonds And here are such small pensions and
алмазы А вот такие мелкие пенсии и
salaries How does it
зарплаты Как так
happen, what do you think, the officials
получается вот вы как думаете чиновники
eat everything up the
то всё сжирает
officials How can you not eat so much
чиновники Как так столько не сожрёшь
if we sell gas at full price  Europe oil
если мы газ продаём во всю Европу нефть
to the whole world gold gas how to plant it all,
во весь мир золото газ как это всё
it’s unrealistic to plant so many that
сажать это нереально столько сажать что
they don’t know the golden
они не знаю золотые
toilets they have time to take even
унитазы они успевают вот ну взять даже
our republic, these Arashukovs
нашей республики вот этих арашуковых
who
которые газом были
owned gas, just rooms rooms
владели просто комнаты комнаты
piled high with heaps of money just to the
заваленные кучами деньгами просто до
ceiling they are now being tried in  To
потолка их же сейчас судят в
Moscow, it’s just that, it’s just
Москве это просто са это просто
redistributing, now someone else
перераспределяет теперь кто-то другой
will collect this money from them, they
будет эти деньги собирать у них они же
couldn’t collect this money without sanction
не могли собирать эти деньги без санкции
from Moscow, I don’t believe that you know, like they’re
из Москвы я не верю такое что знае типа
stealing here and they don’t see it there,
тут воруют а там не видят это такое
yes, but no matter how bad it is  it wasn’t,
да а это насколько бы плохо не было
of course Well, I don’t know I love both my homeland
конечно Ну не знаю Я люблю и свою родину
and I love Russia Well, yes For the Motherland to
и Россию люблю Ну да Чтобы ещё Родина
love you somehow is also true Love
вас любила как-то тоже правда Любовь
must be mutual, it’s
должна быть взаимной
true That’s of course,
правда Это конечно
but for some reason the Motherland doesn’t
но Родина почему-то нас не
love us, yes But this is what I have and, well, close ones
любит да А вот тако у меня и ну близкие
I have relatives and a cousin has been
родственники у меня и двоюродный брат
living there for a
там живёт уже
long time in America.
давно в Америке
Yes, she lives in Detroit
Да в Детройте
and receives
живёт и получает
ma. My cousin also lives. Well, it
ма двоюродной брат тоже жит Ну дядя
turns out that my uncle is also my own aunt who has been living in
получается све тоже родная тётя в
America for many years. She was
Америке уже очень много лет живёт Она
constantly collecting
постоянно собирала
some food that could be
и что-то из еды такое что можно
transported.  Yes, I collected a lot of things in Russia, I
перевозить Да в Россию вещей много
sent huge boxes, I also sent money because
передавала деньги тоже переслала потому
well, the atom in the
что ну были атом во
parcels stopped arriving and,
посылки перестали доходить и
accordingly,
соответственно
everything is yes, but it turns out Well, those of your
всё да а получается Ну вот те ваши
relatives who are in America, what do they
родственники которые в Америке что они
tell you Where is the best place
рассказывают Где лучше
to live? Clearly, no, I can also completely
жить Понятно нет я я тоже могу полностью
agree with  by the fact that in
согласиться с тем фактором что и в
America, life is of course much
Америке Жизнь конечно намного
better in many ways,
лучше во многом плане
and but
и но
even I think it’s even possible to
даже мне кажется даже можно и образ
live a lifestyle despite all this FBI and
жизни несмотря на всю вот эту ФБИ и
everything
всего
else, even there you can raise your
остального даже там можно вырастить и
children and protect your children from
детей оградить от этого
all this, but that’s why How do you
всего а вот из-за чего Как вы думаете
Why do you think America has such a high
из-за чего Америка имеет такой большой
standard of living, why is it much better to live there?
уровень жизни почему там жить лучше
Well, it seems to me that entrepreneurship was there much earlier.
Ну мне кажется там намного ранее
That’s all
именно предпринимательство Вот это всё
somehow, but then again, loans. Yes, if you take
как-то но опять же кредиты Да если взять
big loans from people there, you can
там большие у людей кредиты можно
say that they live their whole lives  in
сказать что они всю жизнь живут в
loans to you, this is your relative
кредитах вам это родственница ваша
telling you that they live in belashka loans all their lives,
рассказывает что они всю жизнь живут в
not not what Nitsa said to those
белашки не не то что Ница сказала тем то
that there are a lot of suns there. Housing on credit
что ВС равно много там Жиль в кредит
doesn’t seem strange to you, they live
вам не кажется что-то странным они живут
on credit Yes, but they pay off this loan without any
в кредит Да но они этот кредит без
problems  and they
проблем выплачивают и они всю жизнь
live in good houses all their lives Yes, they drive
живут в хороших домах Да ездят на
good cars Yes And you live without a
хороших машинах Да А вы живёте без
loan and without good houses without good
кредита и без хороших домов без хороших
cars and without good food How does this
машин и без хорошей еды Как так
happen? They live on credit, but they also
получается Они живут в кредит но и
pay off the loan and their loans are not
кредит выплачивают и кредиты у них не
like in Russia 20  %
как в России 20%
stuck Eh, it’s a pity that the video would be good in
зависло Эх жалко хороший был бы ролик по
length If there was a yes
длине Если бы был да
y Instagram I don’t know why this is
й Instagram Я не знаю для чого це тоб
for why there is to marvel at the ocey face
для чого тоб там дивитись на оцей фейс
Ale for you one two or three clicks
Але для тебе це один два або три клика
Ale ti trimae me and I will be the same in
Але ти тримае мене и я буду казати ва в
I have a bunch of fouls and I will have a
мене там Купа фолов и в мене буде
great attitude so that Robi is cool video
класний настрой чтоб Роби но крут видео
message on my Instagram Popik Andriy
пись на мий Instagram Попик Андрий
so let's go
так давайка
with
с